想象一场强大到足以冲毁道路、
Imagine a storm so powerful it can wash away roads,
摧毁整个社区、甚至让山体崩塌的暴风雨。
destroy an entire neighborhood, or even collapse a mountain.
只需按一个按钮，就能把大自然这股令人恐惧的力量
Now, imagine taking that terrifying power of nature
随意呼来唤去。
and being able to control it with the push of a button.
这正是日本这栋建筑里每天发生的事情。
That's what happens here inside this building in Japan.
那它究竟是什么？又是怎么建成的？
So, what is it? How was it built?
而我又是怎么被忽悠着，跑去地球上雨量最大的地方挨淋的？
And
how was I talked into going for a walk in the rainiest place on earth?
>> 就这样了。
It >> is what it is.
>> 拍到了吗？好，我们现在在这里。
>> Did you get that? So, here we are.
我们来到了东京郊外的大型降雨模拟器。
We're at the large scale rainfall simulator just outside Tokyo in Japan.
"大型"这个形容真的一点不夸张，这地方大得离谱。
Large scale is a good way of putting it cuz it is absolutely enormous.
简直就像一个飞机库。
It's like an aircraft hanger.
比我预想的要大得多。
Much bigger than I was expecting.
说实话，我对这一刻一直有点发怵。
To be quite honest, I've been dreading this moment.
我为今天已经做了好久的心理准备。
I've been building up to today.
制作团队告诉我，美国地质调查局的标准是每小时降雨量8毫米就算大雨，
What the production team have told me is that the US Geological Survey
say that 8 mm of rainfall 1 hour is classified as heavy rain
而我身后这台机器最高能达到每小时300毫米——这根本就不正常。
and that the machine behind me
can go up to 300 mm an hour, which isn't necessary.
自然界里根本不会有这种事。
It's not natural.
我本不必经历这种程度的模拟，但为了让你们看着过瘾，我们还是来了。
I don't need to put in that kind of scenario,
but for your viewing pleasure, we're doing it.
好吧，开始吧。
So, here we go.
我带了把伞，就是那种日本常见的漂亮透明伞，
I've brought my umbrella, which is one of these lovely clear Japanese umbrellas,
但……我不确定它能撑多久。
but um not sure it's going to be enough.
在这场注定要出糗的仪式开始之前，我们先来正经做点工作。
Just before the ritual humiliation, let's actually do some work.
在了解这个地方是怎么建的、为什么要建之前，我们得先聊聊日本住宅的一个奇特现象。
Before we get to know how this place was built and why it's necessary,
we need to discuss the strange quirk of Japanese housing.
你现在看到的，是一栋典型的日本住宅。
What you're looking at here is a typical Japanese house.
虽然大城市里中高层公寓楼林立，
Now, while the major cities are dominated by those mid and high-rise apartment blocks,
但在全国各地的城镇、乡村和郊区，随处可见这样的独栋住宅。
it's houses like these that you're going to find in towns, villages, and suburbs right across the country.
如果你打算移居日本，想淘个便宜，这种房子正合适。而且越老越好。
If you're thinking of moving to Japan and you want to find a bargain,
it's a house like this you'll want. And the older the better.
原因在于，和地球上几乎所有其他国家都不同，日本的住宅价值会
That's because unlike basically every other country on Earth, housing in Japan loses
随着时间流逝而贬值。
value over time.
大约30年后，这样的房子就会被拆掉，换成新的。但这是为什么呢？
After about 30 years, houses like these are going to be knocked down and replaced
by a newer model. But why?
闭上眼睛，想象一下日本的乡村景色。
Well, close your eyes and picture the Japanese countryside.
也许你脑海中浮现的是郁郁葱葱的山峦沟谷、袅袅升腾的温泉，以及古朴的神社庙宇。
Maybe you're imagining lush mountains and valleys, steaming hot springs, and ancient temples.
那是一种与自然深度融合的意境——你的感觉没错。
A place that reflects a deeprooted connection with nature. And you'd be right.
但这种融合，并非总是那么宁静祥和。
But that connection isn't always as peaceful as it seems.
日本的存在，本身就是大自然原始力量的产物。
Japan only exists because of nature's raw power.
数百万年前，巨大的板块构造力将它从海底推出水面，才有了这片土地。
It was forged when massive tectonic forces pushed it out of the sea millions of years ago.
这赋予了这个国家壮丽的地貌，
It gives this nation a stunning landscape,
但也让它成为了全球地震最频繁的国家。
but it's also made it the most earthquake-p prone country on the planet.
日本还要面对世界上一些最猛烈的风暴。
Japan faces some of the world's most violent storms.
台风频繁登陆，带来倾盆暴雨、
Typhoons regularly sweep through, bringing torrential rain,
毁灭性洪涝，以及能把屋顶掀翻的狂风。
devastating floods, and powerful winds that can tear rooftops apart.
仿佛这些还不够似的——日本超过80%的国土被山地覆盖，
As if all of that wasn't enough, with over 80% of Japan covered in mountains,
那些滂沱暴雨还会带来另一个真实威胁：
those torrential storms bring another very real threat.
山体滑坡。
Landslides.
就算你的房子挺过了地震，也可能被一场泥石流瞬间卷走。
Even if your house survives an earthquake,
it could easily be swept away in a river of mud and rock.
很大程度上正是因为这一切，
It's largely because of all this that the idea of impermanence,
"无常"这一概念——万物皆无法永恒——已经深深根植于日本文化之中，
that nothing lasts forever, has been really ingrained in Japanese culture,
就连房子这么"硬"的东西也不例外。
even in something as solid as a house.
这也是为什么许多日本住宅采用半永久性的预制设计——
It's why many homes are built with semi-permanent pre-fabricated designs,
这不是软弱的表现，
not as a sign of weakness,
而是面对难以预测的自然环境所做出的一种聪明而务实的应对。
but as a smart, pragmatic response to an unpredictable landscape.
但这只是应对之策的一半。
But that's only half the response.
另一半，则是处于世界领先水平的防洪城市规划研究，
The other half is worldleading research into floodproof urban planning
以及山体滑坡预测技术。这里是筑波。
and landslide prediction technology. This is Sakuba.
它位于东京东北75公里处，完全有资格被称为日本的科学中心。
It sits 75 km northeast of Tokyo
and has a very good claim to being the scientific center of Japan.
这里既是日本宇宙航空研究开发机构的所在地，
It's home to both the Japanese Space Agency
也是那个名字颇长的NIED——防灾科学技术研究所——的总部所在地。
and the headquarters of the snapply named National Research Institute for Earth Science and Disaster Prevention,
which they helpfully shorten to NIED.
我们在制作关于东京防灾基础设施的纪录片时
Now we came here when we were making our epic documentary
来过这里，但不亲眼看看这栋建筑的内部，实在不甘心就此离开。
about Tokyo's disaster resilience infrastructure and we just couldn't leave without seeing inside this building.
>> 这栋建筑建于1974年，当时正值日本遭受大规模自然灾害冲击的时期。
>> Then this building established is a 1974 and uh this is a big time is coming in the damage.
正是因为洪水和山体滑坡造成了大量损失，我们才在这个设施里研究它们的发生机制。
So damage affected in Japan that now we are research on the mechanism on flooding and the land rise in the using this facility.
类似的模拟装置在世界各地都有，但论规模和纯粹的功率，没有哪个能和这里相比。
There are simulators like these around the world, but none match the size or sheer power of this place.
正如我之前提到的，美国地质调查局将极端强降雨定义为每小时8至10毫米。
As I mentioned, the US Geological Survey classifies very heavy rain
as ranging from 8 to 10 mm per hour.
但在这里，那连第一档都算不上。
But here, that's not even the first rung on the ladder.
>> 我们的系统从每小时50毫米到300毫米，覆盖范围非常宽。
>> In system is a 50 mm power to 300 mm power. This is very wide range.
每小时300毫米，已经非常接近1947年有记录以来最强降雨的峰值了。
300 mm an hour is just shy of the strongest rainfall ever recorded back in 1947.
不过话说回来，今晚的头条是：一个4级飓风正在登陆美国。
But we do begin tonight with this category 4 hurricane slamming into the US.
>> 作为参照，2021年飓风艾达重创美国时，单日最大降雨量也不过200毫米。
>> To put that into context, when the devastating hurricane Ida
hit the US back in 2021,
>> 作为参照，2021年飓风艾达重创美国时，单日最大降雨量也不过200毫米。
the maximum rainfall recorded in one day was just 200 mm.
为什么有必要再现如此滂沱的降雨条件，我们马上会讲到。
We're going to get to why on earth it's necessary to reproduce such torrential conditions
不过，先来说说这个地方是怎么运转的。
shortly, but first off, a bit about how this place works.
这台模拟器由一个巨大的75×15米的机库组成。
The simulator consists of a huge 75x 15 m hanger.
机库内悬挂着由数千根管道和喷嘴构成的格栅结构，
This suspends a lattis work of thousands of pipes and nozzles
高出地面16米——这个高度足以让水滴在落地前达到终速度。
16 m above the ground high enough for the droplets to reach terminal velocity.
这些管道与建筑外部的一根主管相连，水从地下蓄水池泵入其中。
These are connected to a pipe on the outside of the building
which feeds water in from an underground reservoir.
测试区域的外侧设有一排排排水沟，用来收集水流，防止洪涝。
Running along the outside of the test area is a series of drains which collects the water and stops flooding.
这个测试空间被用来测试各种各样的东西，从住宅到自动驾驶汽车，
This test space is used to trial everything from homes to self-driving cars.
再到土壤侵蚀和山体滑坡的实验。
for tests on soil erosion and landslides.
场地的其他区域设有永久性设施，可以搭建各种实验装置。
Other areas of the site have permanent facilities set up where experiments can be constructed.
但等等，不同区域的测试要怎么进行切换呢？
But hold on, how do you carry out tests in different areas?
就在你以为这栋建筑已经够厉害的时候，且听我说：它会移动。
Well, as if this building wasn't impressive enough already, get this. It moves.
这栋建筑是一个可移动系统。
The building is movable system.
你可以看到左右两侧各有一条400多米长的轨道。
You can see the rail long rail 400 over rail in the right left side.
这栋建筑由每个车轮上的独立电动机驱动。
This building is moving by electric motor each wheel.
>> 这栋庞大的建筑实际上就像一节自驱动的火车车厢，移动速度约为每分钟1米。
>> This vast building effectively works as a self-powered railway carriage moving at a speed of about 1 m a minute.
>> 降雨区域超过3000平方米，非常非常大。
>> This is over 3,000 square meter in the rainfall area is very very big.
>> 那么，这一切和日本的住宅有什么关系呢？
>> So how does all this relate to housing in Japan?
其实，山体滑坡在日本非常常见。
Well, landslides are very common here.
它们也非常致命，造成了自然灾害中约一半的死亡和失踪人数。
They're also deadly,
responsible for around half the fatalities and missing people in natural disasters.
日本气象厅会发布预警，帮助人们在最坏的情况发生前撤离家园和工作场所。
Japan's Met Office issues warnings
to help people evacuate their homes and workplaces before the worst happens.
但由于山体滑坡发生得极为迅速，
But because landslides occur so quickly,
能否及时预警始终是一个巨大的挑战。
it's a constant challenge to be able to warn people in time.
这正是酒井博士的研究所要解决的问题。
That's where the work of Dr. Sakai comes in.
>> 我们目前的研究目标，是提升人们面对灾害的韧性。
>> And now our research aim is a resilience for the people.
我们正在开发能够监测土壤状态的传感器。
We are development sensor for the thro condition.
传感器数据可以判断当前状态是否安全。
Sensor data is a checking the safe or not.
实地测试对此至关重要。
It is very important using the positivity testing.
>> 这里研究的独特之处，在于实验的规模。
>> What makes the research here so unique is the scale of the experiments undertaken.
像这样的大规模测试，能为酒井博士这样的研究人员
Tests like this give researchers like Dr. Sakai
提供比小规模项目可靠得多的数据。
much more reliable insights than smaller scale projects.
但让这里独一无二的，不只是实验规模。
But it's not just the size of the experiments here that make this place unique.
要再现各种各样的降雨条件，可不只是把功率调大那么简单。
Being able to reproduce a variety of rain conditions involves more than just cranking up the power.
>> 这套系统能够模拟自然降雨的状态，包括雨滴大小、降落速度和降雨强度。
This system is a like a natural rainfall condition and uh this is a natural rainfall state is a rainfall drop size and the rainfall speed and uh intensity.
>> 正是这种对雨滴大小、速度和强度的精准控制，使这台模拟器独一无二。
>> It's being able to control the droplet size, speed, and intensity that makes this simulator so unique.
它通过四种不同类型的2176个喷嘴喷水，能够模拟0.1至8毫米大小的雨滴。
It sprays water from 2,176 nozzles of four different types
that can reproduce raindrops from 0.1 to 8 mm in size.
雨滴越大，下落速度越快。
The bigger the size of the droplet, the faster it falls.
而喷嘴的高度有助于将雨水均匀分布在测试区域。
And the height of the nozzles helps distribute the rain over an equal area.
深入研究山体崩塌的科学机制，只是这里为拯救生命和财产所进行的研究的一部分。
Discovering more about the science of what causes mountains to collapse
is only part of the research that goes on here to help save lives and property.
这是NIED研究员市古智满（Ichio Cottoman）主导的实验，目标是开发出世界上第一栋防洪屋。
This is an experiment by Ichio Cottoman,
an NED to develop the world's first floodproof house.
通常情况下，洪水几乎无法阻止进入房屋，
Now, flooding is usually impossible to stop in a house
因为进水的地方实在太多，
because there are so many entry points,
但这栋房子安装了一系列防护措施，以阻止洪水灌入。
but this house was fitted with a series of countermeasures to stop it from filling up.
窗户用类似汽车车门上使用的中空密封垫进行了密封。
The windows were sealed with a hollow gasket similar to that used on car doors.
通风口安装了浮球阀，用来阻止水从通风管道倒灌进来。
The air vents are fitted with a float valve which blocks the water coming in through the airway.
进入建筑的管道也安装了逆流防止阀，允许雨水排出，但不允许其进入。
Utility pipes entering the building are also insulated by a backflow prevention valve
which allows rainwater to leave but not enter the property.
这是一项了不起的突破，没有这个设施就根本无法实现。
It's an incredible development that just wouldn't have been possible without this facility.
如果你喜欢这个视频，想要更多来自这个权威频道的内容，好的好的，
If you enjoyed this video and you want to get more from the definitive video, okay, okay,
我还不能就这么结尾。
I can't sign off yet.
团队说一定要加上这段。好吧，来吧各位。
They want to put this bit in. So, here you go, guys.
接下来是我被淋成落汤鸡的几分钟。
Here's a couple of minutes of me getting wet.
说实话，我完全不知道
Now, I'm not really sure
去大型降雨模拟器该穿什么，
what the dress code is for a large scale rainfor simulator to be quite honest,
但我就随便套了些能湿水的衣服，
but I've sort of just worn stuff that can get wet and then they give
然后他们给了我这双橡胶靴，搞得我活像从"乡村人"乐队MV里走出来的。
me these wellies which makes it look like I've walked out the village people.
>> 我现在好恨你。
>> I hate you so much right now.
哦，要开始了。
Oh, here we go.
时刻到了。
The moment has arrived.
那些喷嘴里要冒出什么来？
What is coming out of the park?
两块钱的破伞，给我争口气啊。
I want two quid umbrella. Do me proud.
哦天哪。来了。
Oh god. Here we go.
这对"小雨"来说也太夸张了吧。
It's a bit much for light rain.
真的在倾盆大雨啊。
Absolutely hammering it down.
我的老天爷。
Oh my god.
我为YouTube做的这些事……
Good lord, the stuff I do for YouTube.
我现在只想要一小块干燥的地方。
I want a little island of dry now.
>> 这是小雨。
>> This is light rain.
>> 继续加大。
>> Go for it.
>> 这是小雨。
>> This is light rain.
>> 他刚跟我说这叫小雨，
>> I mean, he's just told me that's light rain,
我的脑子直接短路了，因为我怎么也想不到雨还能比这更大，
which blows my mind because I wouldn't think it could rain more than that,
但好像马上就要来了。
but it's about to apparently.
嘿，这也算是那把两块钱伞的好广告了，对吧？
Hey, it's a good ad for the $2 umbrella, right?
>> 麦克风关掉。好的。
>> Mic off. Yeah.
>> 好的。
>> Yeah.
热。太热了。
Heat. Heat.
希望你们看得开心。
Hope you enjoyed that.
我现在已经彻底湿透了。
I'm now absolutely soaked.
我从没见过这么大的雨。
I've never seen rain like it.
完全没有必要，完全不自然。
It's completely unnecessary, completely unnatural.
但没办法，就这样吧。
But yeah, there you go.
我已经湿透到骨子里了。
I'm absolutely soaked to the bone.
唉，[轻哼]
Well, I [snorts]
我自己是没享受到什么，但如果你享受了这个视频，
didn't enjoy that video, but if you enjoyed that video and you want to get
想要更多来自这个建筑领域权威频道的内容，
more from the definitive video channel for construction,
这个把我扔进各种最湿的地方、
the channel that puts me in some of the wetest places imaginable
让你们坐在干燥处围观的频道——
while you sit in the dry and watch.
请点击订阅按钮。
Hit that subscribe button.
好吧，总之是很湿就对了。
Well, it was wet to be honest.
这是我最大的收获——水。
That was my my biggest takeaway was water.
你看，感觉就像刚经历了一场季风。
You can see it's like it's just been a monsoon.
你现在可能不信，但当时那扇门外什么都看不到。
You wouldn't believe it now, but you couldn't see out that door.
其实里面出乎意料地暖和。
It was actually surprisingly warm.
在日本这么热的天，其实还挺清爽的。
Actually quite refreshing on such a hot day in Japan.
我从来没有被雨砸到过还觉得疼，
I've never had rain actually hit me and hurt me before,
但那次真的，那些雨滴太大了，
but that was like a mixture of the drops were so big.
感觉像是冰雹和三个莲蓬头同时朝你喷水混在一起。真的假的？
Like a mixture of hail and just being hit with three showers at once. Really?
至少 >> 你戴了头盔嘛。
At least >> you got your helmet on, though.
现在没戴。
Not right now.